Guide to the John Howard Griffin Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series XVII.The Decade of the Seventies
  - Subseries XVII.4: Correspondence
    - John Frederick Nims To John Howard Griffin, Chicago & Lake Forest, IL, 1976, (2 t.l.s.) (Box 18, Folder 661)
      [Poet, who was a colleague of Griffin's at the Upper Midwest Writing Conference [This experience was rare for Griffin, who did not "teach writing" on a professional basis.]
    - William Shockley To John Howard Griffin, Stanford, CT, 12 July 1974, (5 page t.l.s. (with carbon reply) (Box 18, Folder 662)
      [Nobel Prize Laureate who invented the junction transmitter used in heart pacemakers, concerning his contention that blacks are genetically inferior to whites. In response to Griffin's July 1974 article in Sepia: "How White Intellectuals Become Racists", Dr. Shockley, surprised at Griffin's objectivity in the piece, nonetheless disagreed vigorously with Griffin's findings.
    - Williams, Robert L. Form letter re. Black Intelligence Test of Cultural Homogeneity (BITCH), St Louis, MO, 1973, (2 page t.l. (with carbon) (Box 18, Folder 663)
      [A black psychologist
    - NAACP To John Howard Griffin, New York, 30 March 1971, (1 page t.l. (signed Ruby Hurley) (Box 18, Folder 664)
    - Marycrest College Regarding Griffin's Commencement Address, Davenport, IA, 1 page, (t.l.s. (with carbon reply) ) (Box 18, Folder 665)
    - Request for Griffin to write an introduction to a sociological text on black determinism, Grand Rapids, MI, [n.d.], (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 18, Folder 666)
    - Flint Community Schools To John Howard Griffin, Flint, MI, 26 Dec. 1972, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 18, Folder 667)
      [About an article following a Griffin lecture there
    - Elizondo, Virgil To John Howard Griffin, San Antonio, TX, 29 Dec. 1978, (2 page t.l.s. (with Table of Contents, 3p.) ) (Box 18, Folder 668)
      [President of the Mexican American Cultural Center in San Antonio Regarding working with Griffin in a study of the effects of racism on the Hispanic community
    - American Society of Magazine Photographers (ASMP) To John Howard Griffin, New York, 1971 & 1977, (2 t.l.s.) (Box 18, Folder 669)
    - The New York Times To John Howard Griffin, New York, 22 Oct. 1970, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 18, Folder 670)
      [Regarding photographs in their travel section
    - Canadian Broadcasting Corporation To John Howard Griffin, Montr al, 1968-1978, (3 t.l.s. (with carbon replies) (Box 18, Folder 671)
      [Concerning the airing of Griffin writings. The letters are in French
    - Hargrove, Marion To John Howard Griffin, Santa Monica, CA, 9 Aug. 1976, (2 page t.l.s. (with carbon reply) (Box 18, Folder 672)
    - Rawhauser, Kurt To John Howard Griffin, San Francisco, 1970, (1 a.l.s., 2 t.l.s. (with related material) (Box 18, Folder 673)
  - Subseries XVII.5: The Noonan File
    Joe Noonan, staff cartoonist for WAY Magazine, first wrote to Griffin in 1971. Soon the two men were corresponding so regularly--and ultimately much more voluminously than Griffin corresponded with anyone in. his lifetime--that the file of Noonan letters to Griffin numbers 1,592 pieces. This is staggering when one considers that this computes to one letter every other day arriving in Griffin's mailbox for nine years (from 1971 until 1980). The pieces vary from postcards and notes to hundreds of single-spaced typed letters (totaling ever 3,000 pages). Noonan was an extremely clever cartoonist and nearly 800 of the 948 envelopes are decorated with his witty cartoons (and nearly all of these take-offs on the ongoing correspondence). Cartoons decorate the letters also; there are an estimated 4,000 original cartoons in the file.. While the accent of the correspondence is one of humor (subtle, bawd, satiric, absurd, and downright silly at times), there are also many Noonan letters that evoke seriousness--discussions of literature, politics, religion and society. Noonan's letters, however, are most notable for their wide range of humor--not only cartoons, but hundreds of loony news items and photographs that were often altered with the cartoonist's sharp pen. Noonan's primary motive was to keep a beleaguered and often very ill author cheered up, laughing, and several steps away from taking it all too seriously. Griffin loved his letters (and envelopes) and perhaps nothing else cheered him so jubilantly in his last years, (1977-1980) especially.. The little we know of Griffin's side of the correspondence (a safe estimate would be about 1,200 letters which are in Noonan's possession) is what is reflected in the Noonan letters. Also, we have an excellent article about the correspondence written by the cartoonist after Griffin's death, and published in a special issue of Way magazine exclusively dedicated to various aspects of the author.
    - Noonan, Joe To John Howard Griffin, Hayword, CA, 1971 & Jan.-June 1972, (20 folders) (Box 19, Folder 674-693)
    - Noonan, Joe To John Howard Griffin, Hayword, CA, July-Nov. 1972, (12 folders) (Box 20, Folder 694-705)
    - Noonan, Joe To John Howard Griffin, Hayword, CA, Dec. 1972-March 1973, (10 folders) (Box 21, Folder 706-715)
    - Noonan, Joe To John Howard Griffin, Hayword, CA, April-Aug. 1973, (7 folders) (Box 22, Folder 716-722)
    - Noonan, Joe To John Howard Griffin, Hayword, CA, Sept.-Dec. 1973, (6 folders) (Box 23, Folder 723-728)
    - Noonan, Joe To John Howard Griffin, Hayword, CA, Jan.-May 1974, (7 folders) (Box 24, Folder 729-735)
    - Noonan, Joe To John Howard Griffin, Hayword, CA, June-Dec. 1974, (10 folders) (Box 25, Folder 736-745)
    - Noonan, Joe To John Howard Griffin, Hayword, CA, Jan.-July 1975, (7 folders) (Box 26, Folder 746-752)
    - Noonan, Joe To John Howard Griffin, Hayword, CA, Aug.-Dec.1975, (6 folders) (Box 27, Folder 753-758)
    - Noonan, Joe To John Howard Griffin, Hayword, CA, Jan.-May 1976, (7 folders) (Box 28, Folder 759-765)
    - Noonan, Joe To John Howard Griffin, Hayword, CA, June-Dec. 1976, (7 folders) (Box 29, Folder 766-772)
    - Noonan, Joe To John Howard Griffin, Hayword, CA, Jan.-Dec. 1977, (11 folders) (Box 30, Folder 773-783)
    - Noonan, Joe To John Howard Griffin, Hayword, CA, Jan. 1978-Dec. 1980, (20 folders) (Box 31, Folder 784-804)
- Series XVIII. The Hermitage Journals
  Subtitled A Diary Kept While Working on the Biography of Thomas Merton, this 231 page published book charts Griffin's 18 visits to Merton's hermitage, from August 5, 1969 through June 15, 1972 (plus three other entries made at his home in Fort Worth, Texas). The edition includes a short preface by Griffin--his last piece of writing composed for publication--and a folio of his photographs of the hermitage and its surroundings. The cloth edition was published by Andrews and McMeel in 1981, the year after Griffin's death; a paperback version appeared a few years later under Doubleday's Image imprint.. Like Black Like Me, this book is a diary set apart from Griffin's ongoing Journal (1950-1980), and was intended as a self-contained work for publication. The scholar will not find either text in the overall pagination of the Journal, even though there are other entries for the years (in which these two books were composed) in that larger 3,000 page compendium. Nonetheless, if one were to read the two published diaries and the Journal chronologically, the overall story of Griffin's life-line continues uninterrupted from 1950 to 1980.. In the case of The Hermitage Journals, the text was first drafted as a diary from 1969-1972. That draft was edited and a second draft was made in 1978-1979 by Griffin in collaboration with Father Tom McKillop, the author's close friend and spiritual guide during the last three years of life. That second draft was edited by Conger Beasley for the cloth edition. But because both Father McKillop and Griffin's widow, Elizabeth, did not favor all the deletions Beasley had made from the second draft, yet a fourth and final draft was agreed upon for cloth publication.. The Hermitage Journals, then, was the last book Griffin prepared for publication under contract, although it appeared posthumously.
  - Diary, Gethsemani, KY & Fort Worth, TX, 1969-1972, (297 pages t.ms. (with Griffin's ms. corrections and revisions) (Box 32, Folder 805-808)
  - Diary, Fort Worth, TX, 1970s, (355 pp. t.ms. (with Griffin's emendations and changes by editor Beasley) (Box 32, Folder 809-817)
  - Andrews, Jim To John Howard Griffin, Shawnee Mission, KS, 1976-1980, (3 t.l.s.) (Box 32, Folder 818)
    [Publisher of Andrews and McMeel. The first letter asks Griffin if he has any current projects in the works (1976); the second letter, dated April 30, 1980, is Andrews' response to a reading of Griffin's hermitage diary--he was so impressed with the manuscript that he offered to publish it and looked forward to actually editing it as well; the third letter acknowledges Griffin's return of the signed contract. [Unfortunately, Griffin and Andrews were not able to work together on the book. Both died before the book was read for production.]
  - Martin, Donna To Elizabeth Griffin, Fairway, KS, 1981-1984, (7 t.l.s.) (Box 32, Folder 819)
    [Vice President of Andrews and McMeel, concerning among other issues, restoring some cuts made by the editor Beasley; also a list of the cuts that were restored
  - Martin, Donna To Tom McKillop, Fairway, KS, 7 July 1981, (2 page t.l.s.) (Box 32, Folder 820)
    [Discussing the editing of the manuscript
  - Griffin, John Howard Production marginalia for The Hermitage Journals: Manufacturing specifications; Two galley pages; Three pages of corrections; ;A list of Griffin's visits to the hermitage; Two sets of footnotes (Box 32, Folder 821)
  - Reviews of The Hermitage Journals (Box 32, Folder 822)
    [When one considers The Hermitage Journals in connection with Black Like Me and Scatttered Shadows, there emerges a fascinating subject for scholarship. These books form an autobiographical trilogy that is unique in subject matter and intensely original in the evocation of these experiences. How many whites have experienced being black? How many social creatures have embraced hermetic solitude? How many have lost their eyesight, endured a decade of blindness and then had vision restored? Surely, these singular realities are among the most misunderstood and nowhere in our literature are they made so understandable from the inside out. Griffin found such human conditions, however contradictory on the surface, profoundly unified in the realm of the spirit. He discovered that being blind or black or being a hermit simply meant being human--that the experience itself was far less difficult and painful than the dehumanizing perceptions of those in the majority, who did not see the individual but only that condition of appearing other than average
- Series XIX.The Griffin Journal, 1950-1980
  "In my teens, when I was a student at the Lyc ee Descartes, in Tours, France," wrote Griffin in the unpublished preface to his Journal, "a man I greatly admired suggested that I begin keeping a journal of my life. He said it was one way of learning to know myself provided I let no one else see it, wrote it honestly and wrote in it even when I felt I had nothing to say.". From the age of sixteen until he was twenty-one, Griffin continued his journal; but when France was about to fall to the Germans, he gave the autograph journals to a schoolmate for safe-keeping, and returned to the states. "Years later when I returned to France [in 19761, I retrieved the journal which had been buried on my friend's father's farm during the war." He began to read his reflections. "It was a sickening experience. Pages were filled with literary analyses, musical analyses, foods we ate, with scarcely a word about the supreme reality of the war which preoccupied us day and night. It was pure escape from that reality rather than any attempt to handle it. I was heartsick to find myself so false.... I burned those pages and did not resume [a journal] until some years later when I was blind and had learned to use the typewriter.". Curiously, it was again on the advice of a man he admired--the theatre critic John Mason Brown--that Griffin began to write. But it was not a journal; it was his first novel, The Devil Rides Outside, written in 1949. His mature Journal was launched in December of 1950, during the third year of sightlessness. When.he was not working on novels or short stories, he poured impressions into the Journal, which became a seedbed for most of work he would publish later. We find in its pages fragments and drafts of stories and novels; essays and articles; voluminous meditations on ethics, religion and philosophy; responses to the music he listened to constantly; discussions of cooking, farming and family relationships; insights into the realities of blindness and how the condition is wrongly perceived by the sighted; speculations on psychology, sociology, anthropology and the arts in relation to the diminishment of culture in America. We hear every tone of voice from the compassionate to the dismissive; styles that range from lyric to polemic, from the scholarly to the absurd. At times he was naive and narrowly opinionated; at other times, measured and wise. He reflected on literature and life--the books he had read (and those which were read to him or recorded on tapes) and all the places he had traveled and lived. He was always a bit nostalgic for the high culture of France and the great joy of learning he had discovered in that adopted land; nostalgic also for the year he spent on a remote island in the South Seas living among the native inhabitants. Conversely, he had been horrified by war--both what he had witnessed working in the French Underground and the devastation of combat while in the Air Force in the Pacific.. Reading the Journal one is always aware that it is an intensely human document--full of contradictions and paradoxes; hope and despair; criticism of the world and self-criticism; fear and anguish over what often did not matter, as well as heroism in the face of what mattered most. The writing is, by turns, elegant and crude; often brilliant and sometimes ignorant; and splattered with passages that roar with comic hyperbole or soar with a spiritual clarity. But always one reads as if one has discovered a secret document; that one is looking over the shoulder of a man who is truely alive in the immense process of becoming a genuine artist and thinker. And later we meet the justly famous author who has absorbed the profound wisdom of humility.. This massive Journal runs to 2,762 pages of single-spaced typed pages. This page count does not include ten autograph notebooks he kept away from the typewriter nor the published books (previously mentioned) that were pulled out of the overall Journal and composed into separate books.. During the period of his blindness--recorded in the Journal from December of 1950 until sight-recovery in January of 1957--he typed almost 900 pages in a span of just slightly more than six years. That is roughly 150 pages each year. Yet, the count for 1951, the first full year of keeping the Journal, is 231 pages (the third highest volume for any year). This was a period of intense introspection for Griffin, he was in the process of making what the French call "the great yes" or the leap of faith from indecision to belief; Griffin became a convert to Catholicism in 1952.. In 1954 we find the second most voluminous year with 255 pages. That year, he was suffering not only from the complications of blindness and diabetes, but he had contracted spinal malaria--a condition which paralyzed him from the waist down and confined him to a wheelchair. All he could do was sit at the typewriter, listen to music, and write.. The entries of 1954 record a very real agony and ecstasy. Griffin experienced the most alienating depths of despair alternating with some of the greatest spiritual heights of his life. Without the love and understanding of his young wife (Elizabeth Holland and Griffin married in 1953), as well as his parents and also her parents--and with absolute faith in God--he would not have survived the ordeal. Instead he wrote about everything that year and drafted over 400 pages of Nuni, his second novel.. In the decade of blindness--from 1947 to early 1957--Griffin composed five novels (two were published, two remain unpublished and the fifth was lost); over sixty short stories (most unpublished); a short book on blindness (Handbook For Darkness); music lectures and articles; and nearly a thousand pages in the Journal. Virtually all of his fiction--literally thousands of pages--were written during the decade of sightlessness. Except for revisions of earlier novels in draft and one short piece of humor ("Pilgrimage"), his career as a fiction writer was over when he regained his sight.. During the 1960s he managed to average over100 pages per year in the Journal, including the second highest page count (248) in 1966. In general, however, these entries move away from introspection toward the concerns of a public life--a-decade which found him away from the studio and his expanding family and in a world of turmoil. His writings were much shorter and their focus was temporal not eternal. He published polemical and journalistic articles on racism, injustice, war, censorship, politics, and lectured extensively on these same issues (and, of course, specifically- on his experiences in Black Like Me, its aftermath, and the civil rights battles that followed. He wrote brilliantly and courageously, and his lectures and writings were in great demand. But the public life took its toll on the books he was forced to leave unfinished (novels as well as Scattered Shadows), and what limited private time that remained was spent with his family and friends and in the darkroom (where his photographic career blossomed), but not in the writing studio. Those years also took their toll on his fragile health. He was no longer blind and the paralysis had lasted only one year, but the stress of his schedule far from solitude increased the debilitating effects of his diabetic condition. He experienced blackouts and exhaustion. His Journal records all this activity in a cryptic rather than expansive manner.. With his appointment as the Official Biographer of Thomas Merton, illness turned toward relative health, exhaustion was replaced by energy, and Griffin once again found spiritual joy in solitude and a fascinating long-range project. The Journal, from 1970-1980 runs about 650 pages--about 65 pages as an annual average with only 1975 accumulating more than 200 pages. This drop in production was a result of the work on the biography and that includes The Hermitage Journals factored out of the equation, as well as a tremendous amounts of photographic work--choices that Griffin was pleased to make, of course. But other factors--not of his choosing--also impacted upon the Journal. There was a significant decline in his health (this is why the entries are more than three times the volume of 1970-1974; he was confined and unable to travel to Gethsemani and Europe where so much research had been accomplished); and there was also the countless intrusions of the curious making pilgrimages to his door.. The Autograph Notebooks, which Griffin considered part of his overall Journal, are from widely different time-frames. Written in spiral notebooks or bound composition books that Griffin carried on his travels when having a typewriter was impossible or inconvenient; these generally reflect a specific event or span of days that can be integrated by dated passage into the overall scheme of his personal Journal.
  - Volume I, Mansfield, TX, 1950/51, (1-242 pages) (Box 33, Folder 823)
  - Volume II, Mansfield, TX, 1952/53, (243-381 pages) (Box 33, Folder 824)
  - Volume III, Mansfield, TX, 1954, (382-637 pages) (Box 33, Folder 825)
  - Volume IV, Mansfield, TX, 1955, (638-758 pages) (Box 33, Folder 826)
  - Volume V, Mansfield, TX, 1956/57, (759-924 pages) (Box 33, Folder 827)
  - Volume VI, Mansfield, TX, 1958/59, (925-1001 pages) (Box 33, Folder 828)
  - Volume VII, Mansfield, TX, 1960, (1002-1065 pages) (Box 33, Folder 829)
  - Volume VIII, Mansfield, TX, 1961, (1066-1157 pages) (Box 33, Folder 830)
  - Volume IX, Mansfield, TX, 1962, (1158-1268 pages) (Box 33, Folder 831)
  - Volume X, Mansfield, TX, 1963, (1268-1337 pages) (Box 33, Folder 832)
  - Volume XI, Mansfield, TX, 1964, (1338-1374 pages) (Box 34, Folder 833)
  - Volume XII, Mansfield, TX, 1965, (1375-1490 pages) (Box 34, Folder 834)
  - Volume XIII, Mansfield, TX, 1966, (1491-1625 pages) (Box 34, Folder 835 & 836)
  - Volume XIV, Mansfield, TX, 1967, (1740-1902 pages) (Box 34, Folder 837)
  - Volume XV, Mansfield, TX, 1968, (1093-2052 pages) (Box 34, Folder 838)
  - Volume XVI, Mansfield, TX, 1969, (2053-2623 pages) (Box 34, Folder 839)
  - Volume XVII, Mansfield, TX, 1970, (2116-2132 pages) (Box 34, Folder 840)
  - Volume XVIII, Mansfield, TX, 1971/72, (2133-2210 pages) (Box 34, Folder 841)
  - Volume XIX, Mansfield, TX, 1973, (2211-2273 pages) (Box 34, Folder 842)
  - Volume XX, Fort Worth, TX, 1974, (2274-2338 pages) (Box 35, Folder 843)
  - Volume XXI, Fort Worth, TX, 1975, (2339-2542 pages) (Box 35, Folder 844 & 845)
  - Volume XXII, Fort Worth, TX, 1976, (2543-2609 pages) (Box 35, Folder 846)
  - Volume XXIII, Fort Worth, TX, 1977, (2610-2682 pages) (Box 35, Folder 847)
  - Volume XXIV, Fort Worth, TX, 1978/79, (2683-2749 pages) (Box 35, Folder 848)
  - Volume XXV, Fort Worth, TX, 1980, (2750-2762 pages) (Box 35, Folder 849)
  - Preface to the Journals, Fort Worth, TX, 1980, (3 page t.ms.) (Box 35, Folder 850)
  - Notebook #1, 1962-1963 (Box 35, Folder 851)
    [Records Griffin's first face to face visit with his mentor, Jacques Maritain, then at Princeton University (October 1962). An augmented discussion of this visit appears in Homage in Words and Pictures. A visit made in March of 1962 to Assumption Univesity in Windsor, Ontario follows; there he had dialogue with Father Stanley Murphy, founder of the Christian Culture Series, and Eugene McNamara, the Canadian literary critic who had written enthusiastically about Griffin's two novels. The third excerpt is about Griffin's first face to face meeting with Thomas Merton at the Abbey of Gethsemani. There is much more about this and other meetings with Merton in A Hidden Wholeness and Follow the Ecstasy. [These handwritten first impressions of two of the thinkers he most admired--Maritain and Merton--give this notebook its rare quality.]
  - Notebook #2, 1966 (Box 35, Folder 852)
    [Records Griffin's photographic experience of the ritual passion performed by the Tarascan culture in the state of Michoacan, Mexico; these are early notes for his published article, "Passion at Tzintzuntzan" (The Griffin Reader). A second section records several pages of notes about Martin Luther King that are the genesis for his piece "Martin Luther King's Moment" (first published in Sign magazine, then anthologized). The third section is a sketch of Gregory Griffin, the author's son, who, at age four began doing photography under his father's tutelage. Gregory published many of his black and white pictures of animals in major photographic journals, beginning at age five up into his teens; he was the youngest member of ASMP (American Society of Magazine Photographers) in the history of that organization--although ASMP did not know the boy was only five at the time, and Griffin kept his age secret for many years after.
  - Lectures #3, 1966, (1 notebook) (Box 35, Folder 853)